We'll be right back.
Welcome back to our series on the parables.
This is week four, so if this is your first time joining us, you've missed a little bit,
but we can catch you up pretty quickly.
Shouldn't be a problem.
Hopefully, you've been following along with us.
We have talked about how one-third of the red letters in the gospel, one-third of the
words that Jesus speaks in the Gospels are spoken in parables.
These are very important lessons, stories that Jesus gives to us, and they're also very
easy to misunderstand or misapply.
It's easy to read things into them that aren't there or to miss things that are there because
we're 2,000 years removed from a culture.
And so, although we don't have time to cover all the parables, my hope is that we give
you some tools in your toolbox so that as you read and come across parables in your own Scripture
reading, because all of you read the Scriptures on a regular basis by yourselves.
Thank you.
So that as you come across these parables, you can hopefully have some tools in your toolbox
to understand them for yourselves.
As we said at the beginning, that parables are indirect communication aimed at challenging
your previously held assumptions.
All of us love to have our previously held assumptions challenged, correct?
Jesus does them creatively.
He goes in through the back door.
He appeals to our imagination, to our emotions.
He doesn't just come right out and say, you're wrong.
He tells you a story that if you take it to heart and walk away with it and think about
it, you'll realize that he was telling you that you were wrong.
And maybe you'll be able to hear it rather than just confronting you directly.
In context, they're directly confronting the nation of Israel's ideas in the first century.
He is speaking to a specific audience for a specific reason.
And so in order for us to understand how they apply to our lives, to interpret them correctly,
we first have to understand the intended meaning.
And then we can get some significance for ourselves.
And last week, I introduced these three categories.
I said that scholars have been trying to categorize parables in many different ways for a very
long time.
And you could find a plethora of categories.
But because we are a church of real people with real lives, I chose a category of only three
so that we would remember them.
The three categories we talked about are the surprising arrival of the kingdom.
So Jesus talks, tells parables in such a way that he talks about the way the kingdom comes in
unexpected ways.
The first century Jews, a lot of them had very concrete ideas about how God's kingdom was
going to come.
And the reality of God's kingdom was different than what they were expecting.
And so Jesus would tell these parables to try and help them broaden their horizons about what
the arrival of the kingdom might look like.
Second category is the surprising ethic of the kingdom of God.
Again, there were previously held assumptions, things about who the kingdom was for, about how
the kingdom would work.
And Jesus tells these parables, one that we're going to cover today about the surprising ethic
of God's kingdom, the invitation to obey it radically.
And the last is as he gets closer to Jerusalem, he gets more and more clear about what he's
saying.
And he has these crisis of choice parables.
The kingdom is coming.
The ethic is surprising.
What will you do about it as the listener?
Will you accept it or will you reject it?
And he talks about the consequences of what happens if you accept it and if you reject
it.
We're going to get to those in a couple of weeks.
They should be very fun.
But for now, that's the context.
That's where we've been.
Does this sound familiar if you've been here for a couple of weeks?
Good.
All right.
Thank goodness.
Let's pray and get started.
Oh, Abba in heaven.
We are so thankful for yet another week with breath in our lungs and an opportunity to sit
here in a group of people that are considering your teachings.
That are open to what you have to say to us.
God, we all come in here with different baggage.
We all come in here with different previously held ideas about you and what you're like and
how you interact with us.
I pray this morning that you would soften our hearts and that we would be able to interact
with your teaching in a way that allows us to be confronted with the truth.
Convicted, challenged, encouraged, and leave this place with a better idea of who you are,
of what you're like, and of what you're inviting us into.
God, do that for your glory and for our good and for the good of our neighbor.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
I don't know if you've ever had the opportunity to ask a question of someone that you looked
up to.
Maybe it was in a college class.
Maybe it was at a Q&A.
You had this opportunity to ask somebody that you look up to a question, or maybe you had
the opportunity to ask a question of someone that is in a position of authority or power
that you totally disagree with, and you thought you were going to ask the question that was
just going to expose their hypocrisy or their bad ideology.
I don't know if you've ever been in this situation.
Maybe you showed up to a town hall to talk to a local politician.
I've been in situations like this previously, and if you're anything like me, I tend to
psychoanalyze conversations that haven't yet happened.
And so I remember these opportunities to ask questions of people either I looked up to or
I was trying to confront, and I would work so hard on wordsmithing, on crafting the perfect
question, and I had two motivations lying behind that.
The first motivation was if I'm asking a question of somebody I look up to, I wanted to word a
question in such a way that I would impress the person I was asking a question of.
You know, they get questions asked all the time, but I wanted to be the one that asked
the question, and they were like, wow, this guy gets it.
You know, what a great question.
Or I worked so hard on crafting a question to expose the false belief of somebody that I disagreed
with.
So again, I don't know if any of you have had these experiences before, but I know for me,
when I've had these opportunities, they often do not go the way that I think they will.
I often don't get the response that I thought I would.
Maybe I'm not as impressive as I think I am, or maybe the person I disagree with isn't as
wrong as I thought they were.
But this is kind of the setting, the context for the parable that we're coming into today.
There is a expert in the Old Testament law, an expert in the Jewish Bible, and he has this
opportunity to come to Jesus with a question.
And we don't fully know what his motivations are, but we know that he has this one opportunity
that he's worked really hard on this question, and that he's going to get an answer that he
does not expect.
It comes in the form of a parable that's very familiar to most of us.
And what I want to do from the outset is I want to caution us to read this parable slowly,
to wrestle with its implications.
I think we have a tendency to read the Scriptures, especially the Scriptures that are familiar to
us.
We read them quickly without nuance in a way that allows us to demonize the perceived enemies
in the text, right?
It's like, ooh, that guy messed up.
And so we read these texts and we think, okay, I'm bad, but I'm not as bad as that guy.
We have a way of demonizing the characters in the story, and we're not able to see the implications
that that might have on our lives.
I think we've done this with the parable of the Good Samaritan.
We've demonized certain characters, and we're not able to see the way in which we play the
part of those characters on a regular basis.
And so we're going to get an answer to this question that's unexpected, and it's going
to challenge us to the core, I think, as it did the original audience.
So let's read it, see what God might have for us.
Luke chapter 10, I'll give you a little bit of time.
I usually like to give you a heads up before I get there.
So Luke 10, if you have, I hear some paper flipping.
I'm so thankful for people with paper Bibles.
Those of you with digital Bibles, you're great too, but, you know, it's good to hold it in
your hands sometimes.
I'm old.
I am old.
All right.
Luke chapter 10, verse 25.
On one occasion, an expert in the law stood up to test Jesus.
Teacher, he asked, what must I do to inherit eternal life?
Classic Jesus fashion, responds to a question with a question.
What is written in the law?
Jesus replied.
How do you read it?
The expert in the law answered, love the Lord your God with all of your heart, soul,
with all of your strength, and with all of your mind, and love your neighbor as yourself.
You have answered correctly, Jesus replied.
Do this and you will live.
But he wanted to justify himself.
I'm going to read that again.
He wanted to justify himself.
So he asked Jesus, and who is my neighbor?
Again, an expert in the Jewish Bible gets his one shot, his one opportunity.
Thank you.
The song lyrics worked last week.
I thought I'd try them again one more time.
His one opportunity to ask Jesus this very important, pressing cultural and theological question,
one that we've probably all wrestled with at one point in our lives.
How do we inherit eternal life?
There has to be more than just this life, right?
All of us have wrestled with this question.
We've gone through the difficulties of life, and we've thought there has to be something more.
How do I get this thing that seems like it's so there and real?
How do I inherit eternal life?
The text says this lawyer, this expert, does it to test Jesus.
Now, we don't know exactly what the motivation is.
We don't know if he thinks Jesus is a heretic that he's trying to expose.
He's the expert.
Jesus has got it wrong, and he's going to ask this pointed question and expose Jesus' false theology.
Or maybe he's genuinely intrigued with the ministry of Jesus.
He's seen the miracles.
He's heard testimonies of all of the incredible things Jesus has done.
But he's got some concerns about his theology.
Whatever the motivation is, he wants to know how Jesus would answer this very crucial question.
He wants to know what Jesus thinks about how to inherit eternal life.
Now, eternal life in this Jewish concept is different than we often think about eternal life in our day.
The Jews in this day had a different idea about eternal life than we do today.
The man wasn't primarily asking about an afterlife destination, which is often what we think about when we talk about eternal life.
We hear evangelists preach to us and say, where will you go when you die?
Do you know for certain you'll go to heaven when you die?
This isn't primarily the thought in Jewish time at this day.
They're thinking primarily about a quality of life that can start now and will last through eternity when God comes back and rules and reigns over the world.
When God returns in Jewish thought, all unrighteous ways of living will be destroyed,
and all righteous ways of living will receive eternal life.
So he's asking Jesus, what can I do?
How do I start living now that will last for eternity?
And again, in classic Jesus fashion, he responds to a question with a question.
Now, before we move on, I just want to tell us that this is a good way.
Like, we could learn a lesson from Jesus responding to questions with questions.
And when you interact with people that disagree with you about theology, when you interact with people that disagree with you about God in general,
I think the tendency is to try and come up with an answer to the question that proves that we've thought it through,
that we have a concrete belief around what we're trying to communicate to them.
And again, I just think this is a total side note, but I think as we interact with people that disagree with us,
we would do well to ask them clarifying questions, to help understand where they're coming from.
And so Jesus does this.
He asks this clarifying question, and the man's response is a home run.
He literally answers the same way that Jesus answers in other parts of the gospel.
He says, love the Lord your God with all of your heart, soul, mind, and strength, and love your neighbor as yourself.
He summarized the whole point of the law.
This has been at the foundation of the Jewish faith.
These two commands are the foundation of Jewish faith.
And Jesus says, you nailed it.
You're in good shape.
Do this and live.
That could have been the end, right?
That's it.
He got his question answered.
He got the right answer.
But it says the lawyer just couldn't help himself.
And I don't blame him.
And I don't think we should jump to condemnation from him too quickly, because I think we do this a lot, more often than we might think.
We try and justify ourselves.
We have all of this good theology in the back of our brain.
We want to obey Jesus, but we think, love God with all of your heart, soul, mind, and strength.
Love your neighbor as yourself.
That's not possible.
That's not a possible thing to accomplish.
No matter how great you are at it, you will not perfectly love God with your heart, soul, mind, and strength.
And you will not love your neighbor as yourself.
And so this lawyer is thinking, okay, I get that that's what we're invited to do, but none of us are doing that.
So seeking to justify himself, seeking to use theology to make him be able to categorize himself as someone that's going to have eternal life.
He says, who really is my neighbor?
Because it can't be everybody.
Everybody can't be my neighbor, or I will never be able to live up to this command.
And again, before we become self-righteous and judge this guy for asking a crazy question,
I think we likely wrestle with the very same question ourselves today, even if we wouldn't say it out loud.
And maybe that's his mistake.
I regularly see Christians in America redefining the word neighbor or love
so that we can continue to think the way that we think and live the way that we live.
We regularly seek to redefine terms so that we don't actually have to think about obeying Jesus's words.
We can obey parts of Jesus's words and justify away the other words by redefining what the words mean.
My question for us is, what if the ideas we're using from Scripture to justify ourselves,
what if they're watered down and curated to promote our own comfort rather than Christ's kingdom?
Would we be willing to let Jesus confront and challenge us in our place of comfort
into a place of self-giving obedience?
Are we willing to consider the reality that maybe we've built a theology
that allows us to cleanly and neatly obey parts of Jesus's teaching
while explaining away the rest of his teaching?
Because I think that's what this lawyer is trying to do.
I think he's trying to create a theological structure,
create a belief about God, an interpretation to the Scriptures
that allows him to continue to live a comfortable life of partial obedience.
Does that sound like the church in America to anybody else but me?
Okay.
We'll get there.
I'm just warming up, guys.
We're just warming up.
Stick with me.
This is exactly what Jesus does.
Again, he goes through the back door.
He challenges this guy's preconceived ideas
by telling an incredibly beautiful parable
that promotes the surprising ethic of God's upside-down kingdom.
Let's read it, and let's read it slowly and thoughtfully.
Remember, the parables were not intended for somebody
to immediately get up and start explaining what they mean.
Let's just allow the words of Jesus
to confront our thoughts and our emotions.
In reply, Jesus said,
a man was going down from Jerusalem to Jericho
when he was attacked by robbers.
They stripped him of his clothes, they beat him,
and they went away, leaving him half dead.
A priest just happened to be coming down the same road,
and when he saw the man, he passed by on the other side.
So, too, a Levite, when he came to the place
and saw him, passed by on the other side.
But a Samaritan, as he traveled, came where the man was,
and when he saw him, he took pity on him.
He went to him, and he bandaged his wounds,
pouring oil and wine,
and then he put the man on his own donkey
and brought him to an inn to take care of him.
The next day, he took out two denarii
and gave them to the innkeeper.
Look after him, he said,
and when I return, I will reimburse you
for any extra expense you may have.
The more I have spent time studying the parables
the last few weeks,
the more I realize how rich in depth they are,
how there's so much theological implications
in each parable,
whether they're two verses long or seven or 10
or whatever it might be,
there's so much going on.
I heard one pastor explain it this way.
He says that the parables are like
if you put on VR goggles
and you had a virtual reality tour of a house,
it's like plopping yourself in the middle of a parable.
You can just walk around
and you can pick up things in the house
and you can investigate them,
you can examine them.
That's often what interpreting the parables is like.
You get plopped into this story
and there's so much cultural context.
There's so many characters.
There's so many things we could pick up
and look and explore
and they almost all have
some theological implications for our lives.
And in this parable,
there's so much going on.
There's so many things that we could pick out.
I had to leave like 70% of the things
that I found interesting in my study
on the cutting room floor,
which is unfortunate,
but it's okay
because we trust the Holy Spirit
to give us the thing
that we need to hear today, correct?
So what I wanna do is,
I think there's two layers here.
There's two rooms that I wanna investigate with
through the parable.
And I think that they,
if we allow them to,
they will challenge us at first,
convict us,
make us see the ways in which we fall short
on such a regular and consistent basis.
And then at the end,
I think we'll be encouraged
and feel loved by God
who forgives us
even in the midst of our failure.
That's the plan for the rest of the time.
Does that sound okay?
All right,
so the first layer of this parable
that I wanna look at
is the most obvious intended implication
for the lawyer,
for the expert of the law,
and subsequently,
anyone seeking to understand
and apply the command
to love the Lord your God
with all of your heart, soul, mind, and strength
and to love your neighbor as yourself.
Jesus is telling this story
to answer his question,
who is your neighbor?
How do I love God
and love my neighbor fully?
In 2,000 years removed
from this cultural moment,
it seems like a pretty cut and dry story
about some self-righteous religious jerks
getting God wrong
and a religious outsider
getting God right.
Does that sound
like a decent cursory reading of the text?
But I think this distant approach,
again,
allows us to keep from seeing
how the attitudes of the priest
and the Levite
might still be very alive
in our hearts today.
We have to humanize these characters.
We have to realize
the context that they were in,
the tensions that they were dealing with,
because all of us,
all of our lives are complicated
and nuanced,
and none of us
have such simplicity
that we like to read in the text.
And so,
I want to think about this.
The Levite and the priest,
they had a significant role
in the life of the nation of Israel
during a very tumultuous time.
These men were tasked
with preserving
the very identity
of their nation
in the midst of tremendous pressure
both inside
and outside their ranks.
There was corruption
in the Jewish world.
outside the Jewish world.
There was persecution
of the people of Israel.
And it was their job
to hold the line,
to lead by example
on obedience to God
and proper worship of Him
in a time when compromise
and rebellion was rampant.
I'm not saying
they did the right thing
because they didn't.
But if we ignore
the complex factors
involved in their decision,
we might miss the ways
that we make similar decisions today.
I think Christians in America,
we have this pressure
with outside forces coming in
and with inside forces
redefining things
that we have held true
for 2,000 years.
We feel this pressure
to hold the line on truth,
to hold the line
on obedience to God
and worship of God.
And I think sometimes
I see this in our day
and age today
where sometimes
we feel this pressure
and we're trying
to hold Christianity together.
We're trying to be obedient.
We're trying to be faithful.
And we're so focused on that
that we miss obedience
to God all around us.
And I think it would be easy
for an outsider
to look in and say,
oh, you Christians,
like you're really good
at saying the right things,
at putting the right things
on paper,
but what are you doing
with the people around you
who are suffering?
So I don't think it's,
I don't think we can get away
with just like demonizing
these characters
and justifying it away.
I think they had three
primary tensions
that they were wrestling with.
The first is fear of safety.
It's a very dangerous road.
It's very possible
that the robbers
who beat this man
half to death
were using this half dead man
as a trap
to get some compassionate person
to come in
so that they could beat him
half to death
and take all of his stuff,
right?
There's fear of safety
and security in this text.
It could be easy
for somebody
who feels self-important,
who feels like their role
as a priest or a Levite
serving God in the temple,
they can't take the risk
of getting hurt
because if they get hurt,
then the temple's
gonna be short-staffed,
right?
The worship of God
could go by the wayside.
I've gotta make sure I'm safe.
There's purity laws
in the Old Testament
that would have
made it very embarrassing
and costly
and inconvenient for them
if they happened
to touch a dead person.
So they don't even
get close enough
to know whether or not
he's dead or not.
He looks dead,
they assume he's dead
and they're not going
to take on
the difficulty
of dealing with this person
even though
in many Jewish teachings
of the day
taking care of a dead person
was like something
that they absolutely
should have done.
So I don't know
if it's fear
or purity laws
or their theology
notice that there's
a debate going on
around at this time
about who the neighbor
actually is in the text.
Many Jews would define
loving your neighbor
as yourself
as just Jewish people
while others would say
no, it's everybody
and there's this theological
debate going on
within the nation of Israel
at the time
and you'll notice
in the parable
that Jesus leaves this man
culturally ambiguous.
he's half dead
and naked,
he's got no clothes on
and he can't talk.
Those would be
the two primary ways
for somebody to know
where you were from
in this day and age.
They'd listen to your dialect
and they'd know
if you were Jewish or not
and they'd see
how you were dressed
and so there's no way
for these priests
and this Levite
to know whether or not
this is a Jewish person
or not and so maybe
they've got this theology
that I'm only supposed
to love my Jewish
brothers and sisters
and I don't know
if that's a Jew or not
so I'm not even
going to go near it.
Whatever reason
or combination of reasons
led these two
to decide their lives
were more important
than this man in need
and what Jesus does next
would have been
extremely shocking
and emotionally provoking.
He picks the category
of people
that the Jews
hated the most
to make the hero
of the story.
The priest
and the Levite
miss the opportunity
to love their neighbor
as their self
and in walks
the Samaritan.
The Samaritans
were descendants
from the 12 tribes
of Israel
but during the Assyrian
captivity were forced
to intermarry
with Gentiles
leading them
to incorporate
idol worship
within their worship
of Yahweh.
They actually built
for themselves
a separate temple
outside of Jerusalem
and they claimed
that they were truly
worshiping Yahweh
which led to this
deep hatred
between the Jews
and the Samaritans.
As I was studying
it this week
I heard somebody
refer to
close enemies
versus distant enemies
and I thought
this was so helpful.
I think
for many of us
it's easy
for us
to extend
more compassion
on what we would
consider distant enemies.
People that just
totally disagree with us
totally like
they're just totally
out in left field
in our minds
they don't have
anything in common
with us
they don't hold
any of the
presuppositions
that we hold
it's easy for us
to say
well they don't know God
and so of course
they're gonna act that way
I can have compassion
I can have empathy
but okay
now these people
who are claiming
to know God
who are worshiping
this way
who are living
who are affirming
these things
it's harder
for us to have
compassion on people
that are close enemies.
Am I the only one?
We often have
less empathy
for people
who claim
to know God
but act differently
than we think
they should
and that's how
the Samaritans
were to the Jews
they were close
enemies
and this
close enemy
of the Jews
forsakes
any fear
of safety
any inconvenience
of expense
any potential
feeling of
self-importance
and he moves
towards this
image bearer
of God
with compassion
he gets his
hands dirty
he bandages
his wounds
he nurses
him back
to life
from the brink
of death
he stays
with him
overnight
in a hotel
and gives
the hotel
manager
two weeks
worth of room
and board
out of his
own pocket
I don't know
how many
of you
have two
weeks
worth
of holiday
in
sitting
in your
bank
account
it's a lot
of money
not only that
he says
I'm gonna come
back
in any
extra expense
any
if you have
to pay
more than
these two
denarii
if you have
to pay
more than
this two
two works
with weeks
worth
of room
and board
I will pay
you back
for taking
care of this
person
I've never
met before
and don't
know anything
about
I don't even
know why
he ended up
halfway dead
in a ditch
it might be
all his fault
but I am
going to
go out
of my
way
to extend
compassion
and mercy
and love
to this
person
and I hope
we can see
the irony
here
two men
who have
given their
lives to
serve
the God
whose primary
commands
they've given
their whole
life to
serve Yahweh
and his
primary commands
are to love
God and to
love your
neighbor as
yourself
and they
are the
ones who
refuse to
love their
actual
neighbor
while their
enemy with
bad theology
chooses to
sacrificially
demonstrate
obedience to
these primary
commands
my question
for us
is what
good is
good theology
without
obedience
who cares
if we have
all of our
doctrines
right
if we don't
love our
neighbor
my question
is has
good theology
become the
primary pursuit
of the
American church
while neglecting
basic
obedience
maybe it's
just me
because I
live in
these more
scholarly
worlds
but I
just see
so many
Christians
dividing
and fighting
and disunifying
over arguments
about how to
interpret certain
texts of the
Scripture
and I don't
know about you
but last time
I checked
the last
prayer that
Jesus prayed
about the
church was
that they
would be
united
with one
another
and so
out of a
desire to
have our
theology
right
we break
unity with
our brothers
and sisters
in Christ
what good
is good
theology
without
obedience
Jesus
reengages
as he
finishes
this
masterful
story
verse 36
he says
which of
these three
do you
think was
a neighbor
to the
man
who fell
in the
hands
of the
robbers
the
expert
in the
law
replied
the
one
who
had
mercy
on
him
Jesus
told him
go
and do
likewise
notice that
Jesus
flipped the
question
the question
that the
expert
asked him
was
who is
my
neighbor
and the
question
Jesus
asked him
in response
is
which of
these
people
do you
think
was
a
neighbor
Jesus
says
the
question
for
God's
people
shouldn't
be
who
is
my
neighbor
but
am
I
acting
like
a
neighbor
again
it's
easy
to read
the story
quickly
and mock
the priest
and Levite
however
as I
slow down
to ponder
this story
more carefully
this week
I realize
that many
Christians
to this
day
still limit
or refuse
to tangibly
love suffering
people around
us
out of fear
self-preservation
or comfort
and we hide
behind our
theology
that allows
us to
justify
and dehumanize
entire
categories
of people
who are
image
bearers
of
God
and we
dehumanize
them as
less than
human
and unworthy
of love
and compassion
I bet you guys
liked it better
when this was a
super familiar
heartwarming
story
I did too
I gotta be honest
with you
I was excited
about preaching
this and now
I'm nervous
because it's
extremely
challenging
if we
allow it
to sit
with us
if we
allow
ourselves
to feel
the tension
that the
Levite
and the
priest
might have
felt
if we
realize
some of
the ways
in which
we do
the same
things
some of
us have
made our
political
ideology
so central
to our
identity
that we
let our
politicians
disciple us
into the
dehumanization
of entire
categories
of people
and some
of you
heard that
and you
got really
excited
because you
think I'm
talking about
the other
party
both sides
do this
and both
sides
use the
Bible
to justify
their actions
and at the
end of the
day
most of our
politicians
not all
of them
but many
of our
politicians
their primary
concern
is accumulating
more power
for themselves
not obeying
the Scriptures
and so if
we allow
our politicians
to disciple
us into
how to
categorize
people
who is
our neighbor
well this
person is
your neighbor
and this
person isn't
your neighbor
the person
who voted
for him
is a good
neighbor
the person
who voted
for him
isn't a
neighbor
this person
who's fleeing
from difficulty
in their
current nation
they're definitely
not a neighbor
because they
weren't born
here and they're
not legal
and so none
of that
matters
if we
allow our
politicians
to redefine
full categories
of people
into not
neighbors
we will not
obey the
commands of
Jesus
the command
of Jesus
is to love
your neighbor
as yourself
and he
intentionally
leaves this
person ambiguous
to say
anyone
with breath
in their lungs
is an image
bearer of God
worthy of
love
and affection
worthy of
compassion
and empathy
no matter
their circumstances
if they're
in a hole
that they
dug themselves
into
empathy
love
love that
we have
received from
God
that we are
invited to
extend
to others
now
I realize
that this
seems
just like
the lawyer
a task
that is
impossible
so impossible
it could
cripple us
with inaction
all of us
are surrounded
by people
who are needy
and suffering
how could we
possibly obey
this command
how could we
love every
single person
in need
how could we
stop what
we're doing
every moment
of the day
to help
somebody
who is
suffering
I love
this quote
from Klein
Snodgrass
fun name
really fun
name
I think
he gives us
some clarity
here on how
to practically
live this out
he says
the New Testament
is more an
identity book
than it is a
guidebook
it tells
what Christian
character is
not what
actions must
be done
in each
case
disciples
of Jesus
are those
who refuse
boundaries
for the
identification
of neighbor
and instead
love even
their enemies
with that
identity
in place
each person
must determine
what path
of wisdom
best expresses
that identity
so what he's
saying here
is he's saying
the New Testament
doesn't tell you
how to live
every second
of every day
it gives you
an identity
that then you
get to by the
power of the
Holy Spirit
live out
every second
of every day
our identity
as Christians
is a people
who refuse
to define
certain people
as neighbors
and certain
people not
as neighbors
our identity
as a Christian
is to see
every image
bearer of God
as our neighbor
to be loved
now within
each momentary
decision that
you have
because you
have to go
about life
you have to
do things
go to work
you have to
take care of
your family
there are
things that
you have to
do
there are
always going
to be
suffering
people around
us
Jesus said
that
you by
the power
of the
Holy Spirit
get to be
led by the
Spirit
to express
that love
to those
around you
there's freedom
here
but we have
to do it
with accountability
because if we're
not careful
we will lump
ourselves into
a group of
people that
have redefined
love or
redefined
neighbor
and when we
don't love
our neighbor
as ourself
they're like
no you're
good
that's not
your neighbor
or that's
not what
love means
we've got to
do it
by the
power of
the Holy
Spirit
in community
with our
brothers and
sisters in
Christ
this is the
first layer
of meaning
Jesus wants
us to see
stop asking
who is my
neighbor
and start
asking yourself
am I
acting like
a neighbor
am I
redefining
love or
neighbor so
that I can
justify myself
and my
behaviors
the things
that I'm
already
comfortable
with doing
the second
meaning is
a deeper
meaning
for those
with eyes
to see
and ears
to hear
remember we
said earlier
in our series
that parables
are intended
to both
conceal and
reveal elements
of the
kingdom
depending on
the heart
posture of
the recipient
that's what
the parable
of the
sower was
all about
what is
your soil
like what
is your
heart like
are you
able to
receive the
truths of
the kingdom
or are you
rejecting them
with a
hard heart
and I
think for
the disciples
who had
been with
Jesus
and heard
teaching
after teaching
of the
upside down
values
of the
kingdom
explanations
about how
he would
have to
suffer
and die
and be
resurrected
this has
already
happened
in Luke
they've
already
heard him
say
he's
gonna have
to suffer
and die
they've
witnessed
miraculous
things
like him
touching
leopards
to heal
them
and raising
a little
girl
from the
dead
might
they
and
us
by
extension
be
invited
to see
a deeper
meaning
behind
this
powerful
story
I
think
both
layers
can be
true
although
I
think
Jesus
is
intending
to answer
the
lawyer's
question
about
who
and how
to treat
our
neighbors
he also
wants us
to see
those of us
who have
eyes
who are
willing
open
he wants
us
to see
how God
might bring
the
kingdom
to us
unexpectedly
and
sacrificially
just like
the
Samaritan
was the
unexpected
hero
in the
story
so too
would
Jesus
be
the
unexpected
Messiah
who
would
come
not as
a
conquering
king
on a
horse
but a
suffering
servant
on a
donkey
this
word
phrase
that
Jesus
uses
of the
Samaritan
NIV
says
he took
pity
on him
the
Greek
is
more
compassion
and it's
a
complex
phrase
that's
used
multiple
times
in the
Gospels
and it's
only ever
used
of Jesus
having
compassion
on people
it's
this
deep
in the
bowels
sobbing
compassion
for the
brokenness
of humanity
Jesus
has
compassion
on you
and on
me
when we're
half dead
naked
laying
in a
trench
he does
something
about it
he takes
action
when we
are
helpless
and when
he didn't
have
to lay
down
his
life
he chose
just like
the
Levite
and the
priest
did
nothing
to help
this
dying
man
so
too
will
obedience
to the
law
not be
able
to do
anything
for those
of us
who are
dead
in our
sins
we need
more than
moral
obedience
we need
a sacrificial
servant
who would
step down
from his
place of
privilege
to bring
us back
to life
this
is the
gospel
we were
dead
in our
trespasses
and our
sins
Jesus
brought us
back to
life
we were
laying
half dead
in a
trench
unable
to do
anything
about our
circumstances
and Jesus
came to
us with
compassion
and empathy
when we
did
nothing
to
deserve
it
nothing
to
earn
it
so you
might be
thinking about
certain categories
of people
and you
might be
thinking
but they
didn't do
anything
to deserve
it
they don't
do
anything
to earn
it
respectfully
Jesus
doesn't
care
every
image
bearer
of God
is our
neighbor
we need
to see
them
with
compassion
and with
empathy
we need
to see
one another
with compassion
and empathy
no one
has seen
God
but if
we love
one another
God's
love
becomes
demonstrable
it becomes
visible
to those
around us
this parable
is both
a parable
about how
to receive
the sacrificial
love of
God
that brings
us from
death to
life
and then
how to
take that
love
and extend
it
to the
suffering
and dying
people
around us
so if
you're like
me
and you
read the
Scriptures
and you
want to
find yourself
in them
am I
the only
one
you ever
read the
Bible
and you're
like
where am
I
at
in
the
story
you
likely
aren't
the
priest
you
aren't
the
Levite
or the
Samaritan
although
each of
them
have
implications
for our
lives
no you
and I
are
most
likely
and most
relevantly
in this
story
either
the
half
dead
man
in a
trench
or the
innkeeper
if you're
in here
and you've
never
trusted
Christ
for
salvation
the
Scriptures
define
all
people
who
have
not
come
to
the
knowledge
of
faith
the
trust
of
Jesus
over
their
lives
it
explains
defines
us
as
dead
in our
trespasses
and sins
no good
works
no amount
of therapy
or religious
experiences
can make
you alive
you have
to surrender
yourself
to the
one who
stepped down
from his
place of
privilege
and power
to make
a way
for you
to be
brought
back
to life
so if
you're
here
and you've
never
trusted
in
Jesus
I
hope
that
you
hear
in
this
story
a
depiction
beautiful
incredible
depiction
of the
gospel
that
Jesus
stepped
down
from
heaven
when
you
were
half
dead
lying
in
a
trench
and
at
great
expense
to
himself
the
greatest
expense
laid
down
his
life
so
that
you
could
have
life
I
implore
you
to
wrestle
with
that
this
week
to
come
talk
to
me
or
somebody
at
the
prayer
tent
maybe
you've
made
that
decision
recently
and you
haven't
been
baptized
we've
got
baptism
coming
up
this
declare
the
people
around
you
that
I
was
a
dead
man
in
a
trench
but
Jesus
brought
me
back
to
life
maybe
you're
in here
and you're
a struggling
believer
I love
that the
man's
described as
half
dead
I feel
like many
of us
can
relate
we've
trusted
in
Christ
for
salvation
but
we're
trying
to
clean
ourselves
up
apart
from
him
I
just
feel
like
the
Lord
wants
me
to
tell
you
this
morning
stop
trying
to
overcome
your
doubts
fears
your
bitterness
and
your
addictions
on
your
own
salvation
from
Jesus
grace
from
Jesus
isn't
just
for
eternal
salvation
it's
for
power
to
overcome
whatever
you're
going
through
right
now
surrender
to
Jesus
and
get
plugged
into
Christian
community
that's
what
we're
all
about
here
we
want
to
be
a
place
where
real
people
with
real
lives
can
grow
in
their
faith
together
none
of us
have
it
all
together
but
by
the
power
of
the
spirit
of
God
we
can
pursue
obedience
encouragement
and
accountability
lastly
if
you're
in
here
and
you're
like
I'm
doing
pretty
good
I
think
we
could
put
ourselves
in
the
place
of
the
innkeeper
Jesus
brings
the
innkeeper
this
half
dead
man
that
he's
nursed
back
to
life
and
he
entrusts
him
with
the
care
of
this
person
he
gives
them
two
dinari
and
he
says
take
care
of
him
and
I'm
coming
back
does that
sound
anything
like
you've
heard
before
I've
done
something
I'm
doing
something
and
I'm
coming
back
who
has
Jesus
brought
into
your
life
to
sacrificially
love
what
skills
and
resources
has
he
entrusted
you
with
to
serve
and
when
he
returns
will
he
find
will
he
find
you
faithfully
taking
care
of
the
people
that
he's
entrusted
you
with
which
leads
us
to
got
time
good
the
lawyer's
original
question
one that
we've
all
wrestled
with
what
must
I
do
to
inherit
eternal
life
I
did
my
best
to
summarize
Christ's
answer
to
this
man
like
this
true
life
both
now
and
for
eternity
is
found
through
knowing
loving
and
obeying
the
God
revealed
to
us
in
Jesus
this
is
the
gospel
we
have
to
understand
who
Jesus
is
and
what
he's
done
and
who
we
were
before
him
we
have
to
come
a
place
of
knowledge
and
appreciation
affection
for
God
starts
with
us
receiving
knowing
loving
Jesus
and
moves
forward
into
us
taking
the
love
that
we
have
received
and
extending
that
love
to
others
through
obedience
do
we
truly
understand
how much
God
loves
us
and
what
he
did
to
save
us
do
we
actively
and
intentionally
abide
in
that
love
on
a
regular
basis
and
out
of
an
overflow
of
that
love
are
we
seeking
to
demonstrate
that
love
to
those
around
us
even
when
it's
inconvenient
or
costly
this
is
the
surprising
kingdom
ethic
this
is
the
parable
of
the
Samaritan
is
what
it
invites
us
to
wrestle
with
the
question
that
Jesus
might
have
ears
to
hear
this
has
been
a
tough
don't
have
all
the
answers
I've
got
a
lot
more
questions
than
I
had
a
week
ago
so
thanks
for
granting
me
the
privilege
of
spending
my
week
wrestling
with
this
text
I
just
pray
that
we
as
a
people
would
take
these
words
seriously
and
if
there's
been
some
things
that
I've
said
that
have
frustrated
you
that
have
caused
you
to
shut
down
or
justify
yourself
by
explaining
away
why
I'm
wrong
and
you're
right
first
there's
a
very
real
possibility
that
I'm
wrong
not
denying
that
but
second
go
back
to
the
words
of
Jesus
yourself
and
let
him
confront
you
wrestle
with
what
he's
saying
to
you
not
what
I'm
saying
to
you
and
be
willing
to
surrender
whatever
identity
you have
created
for
yourself
that
allows
you
to
have
a
Christian
life
that
doesn't
do
anything
Christ
invites
us
to
do
we're
going to
take
communion
together
and we
didn't
warn you
that that
was
happening
so some
of you
might have
gotten it
on your
way
in
if
not
take
the
time
now
you
want
to
lead
us
in
some
how
he
loves
let's
receive
the
love
of
God
over
us
as
we
prepare
to
take
communion
*music*